A Guide to the Tanbark Industry in the Shenandoah Valley Oral History Collection: SdArch 4
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Tanbark Industry in the Shenandoah Valley Oral History Collection
1987, 1991
Special Collections, James Madison University
Barb, Mia
Bolgiano, Chris
Coleman, John
SdArch 4
245
.25 cubic feet; 4 folders, 4 audiocassettes, 3 cds
The Tanbark Industry in the Shenandoah Valley Oral History Collection, 1987, 1991, is comprised of audio interviews, transcripts, photographs, and a background paper, documenting the history of the bark peeling industry in the Shenandoah Valley.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Collection was donated in 1991 by Mia Barb.
Bio/Historical Note
Two of the oral histories were created by Mia Barb, an undergraduate at JMU, who completed the project as an intern in Special Collections during the summer of 1991. The internship was a joint project between the Carrier Library, Special Collections and the U.S. Forest Service. The oral history interview with D.D. Wilkins was conducted by Chris Bolgiano, head of Special Collections, and John Coleman, who worked for the U.S. Forest Service.
Scope and Content
The Tanbark Industry in the Shenandoah Valley Oral History Collection, 1987, 1991, is comprised of audio interviews, transcripts, and a background paper, documenting the history of the bark peeling industry in the Shenandoah Valley. The collection includes interviews that explore the various processes used to produce leather, including references to the peeling, grinding and extracting of bark to yield the tannin (tannic acid) which was used to tan animals skins and hides. The interviews focus specifically on the mills, extract factories and tanneries in the Shenandoay Valley, including the Timberville extract factory, and the Ziegler, Elkton and Houck tanneries of Rockingham County, Virginia.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Tanning -- Virginia -- Rockingham County; Tanning -- Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.); Bark peeling -- Environmental aspects; Bark -- Harvesting; Bark peeling -- Economic aspects; Bark -- Virginia -- Rockingham County; Leather industry and trade -- Virginia -- Rockingham County; Tanneries -- Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.); Tanneries -- Virginia -- Rockingham County; Industries -- Virginia -- Rockingham County -- Sources; Tanners -- Virginia -- Rockingham County
Genre and Form Terms:
oral histories (literary works)
- 4-1: Tanbark Industry Background Paper and Photographs (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  13-leaf monograph describes the tanning industry in the United States and in particular the Shenandoah Valley. Both general information about the industry and specifics about the tanbark process are included. The various processes used to produce leather are described, including references to the peeling, grinding and extracting of bark to yield the tannin (tannic acid) which was used to tan animals skins and hides. References are made to American tanneries in general; specific information is supplied about bark mills, extract factories and tanneries in the Valley--including the Timberville extract (ooze) factory, and the Ziegler, Elkton and Houck tanneries of Rockingham County, Virginia. Transcription summary and letters are related to an interview with Mrs. Lettie Albrite and niece (Ms. Turner-Ritchie) conducted by Mia Barb, at Camelot Nursing Home, Harrisonburg, Va. on March 29, 1991. Refers to Mrs. Albrite's reminiscences of the bark extracting factory at Timberville, Va.; mentions Gen. John Roller, owner. Full transcription and tape of this interview are unavailable.
- 4-2: Leecy Yankey interviewed by Mia Barb, February 26, 1991
  This interview records the reminiscences of Mr. Yankey's days as a bark peeler of chestnut oak and hemlock in the Allegheny mountains in areas around Petersburg, Moorefield, Franklin, Cheat Mt., Cass, and Lost City, W. Va. Describes the process of peeling and transporting the bark. Mentions social life and medical care in camps. Refers to paper mill strike in Davis; work in the Timberville, Va. Peach Cannery. Recorded at the home of Mr. Leecy Yankey of Bergton, Va. on Feb. 26, 1991.
  - Transcript and Supporting Documents, February 26, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Original audiocassette, February 26, 1991 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA004-CS-001)
  - Original audiocassette, February 26, 1991 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA004-CS-002)
  - Preservation master cd (Box 1, Cd SA004-OP-001)
- 4-3: Kale Barb interviewed by Mia Barb, March 9, 1991
  This interview records the reminiscences of Mr. Barb's days as a bark peeler of black, red and white oak in the Allegheny mountains region of Rockingham County, Va., in particular Little Turley Mt. Describes the process of peeling and transporting bark including detailed information on how draft animals (horses and mules) were used. Mentions social life, etc. in the camps. Worked for Neff Lumber Mills at Skidmore Fork Lumber Camp, etc. Recorded at the home of Mr. Kale Barb of Fairway Hills, Harrisonburg, Va. on March 9, 1991
  - Transcript and Supporting Documents, March 9, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Original audiocassette, March 9, 1991 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA004-CS-003)
  - Preservation master cd (Box 1, Cd SA004-OP-002)
- 4-4: D. D. Wilkins interviewed by John Coleman and Chris Bolgiano, September 25, 1987
  This interview records the reminiscences of Mr. Wilkins' (D.D. "Hun") days as a bark peeler of chestnut oak and hemlock in the Alleghenny mountains of West Virginia, especially in and around Lost River (also Stump's Run, Moorefield, Lost City and Trout Run). Mentions chestnut blight; blizzard of April 27, 1928. Mentions the Maryland-W. Va. Lumber Co., Natrick Lumber Co. and Williamsport, Md. Tannery. Reminiscences about conditions in the camps
  - Transcript and Supporting Documents, September 25, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Original audiocassette, September 25, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA004-CS-004)
  - Preservation master cd (Box 1, Cd SA004-OP-003)